collective insights as a voyage through
topics and technology is revolutionizing
human wellbeing groundbreaking
approaches for a better world and a
better life away you
[Music]
to collective insights
welcome everybody this is the neuro
hacker collective podcast my name is
Daniel schmuck murder I'm with the
research and development team here at
neural hacker and we are delighted to
have dr. nafisa harpeia with us today
talking about the role of the microbiome
dysbiosis and chronic infection on
mental emotional psychological cognitive
health and well-being a huge important
topic that we haven't got to dive into
on the podcast yet and so dr. par Pia is
a naturopathic integrative doctor she
did her schooling at Bastyr University
and then actually went and did a year of
training at the Sofia Clinic with dr.
Kling heart and you know some of the
world-renowned doctors there working on
complex chronic illness cases infection
toxicology many of those underlying
drivers of complex illness and has
worked in a number of cutting-edge
facilities since then she's currently at
Gordon Medical which is a largely
focused on chronic complex illness in
the Bay Area and they're doing some
really pioneering work on clinical
metabolomics but her practice is kind of
half-and-half between people who are
seeking optimization and life extension
on the wellness side and people who are
working with chronic illness and
obviously infection and microbiome is
just one part of it but it's a part that
she's done a lot of work with so we
wanted to dive into that so nafisa
welcome thank you for being here today
thank you for having me Daniel such an
honor yeah so we're we're happy to have
you and Anna Pisa and I have had the
opportunity to actually work on a few
people's cases together and to actually
kind of compare notes on addressing
things like infection so knew this would
be fun so for a lot of people the idea
of chronic subclinical infection is it
doesn't even make sense right the way
there is a classic idea of acute
infection you have C difficile and you
have to get on antibiotics or you're
going to die or you have you know the
acute flu or Mercer or whatever it is
but asymptomatic or where the symptoms
are you know delayed in time or
non-obvious infection is something that
the integrative functional naturopathic
medicine community is focused on for a
long time many traditional systems of
medicine have is not one of the common
parts of Western medical focus except in
cases where now you know there's more
awareness of things like the role of h
pylori and stomach cancer or you know
viruses and certain kinds of cancer so
that's you know increasing an awareness
but can we just start by talking about
chronic infection that is not acute
what's that about yeah so there can be
infections in certain areas of the body
dental and sinuses but people have no
idea about it essentially these
illnesses are contained in the immune
system they're completely without
symptoms um it can be viruses bacteria
even lying and co-infections people
people can be walking around this
infection no idea about it until there's
a stressor and that stress depletes the
immune system all of a sudden know
they're walking around with symptoms so
I see a lot of patients like that
stresses stressors can be physical often
motor vehicle accidents they can be
emotional or mental stresses I think
that brings me immune system down and
that allows for the microbes to fester
suddenly the person showing symptoms so
one of the key ideas here is that if
someone starts showing symptoms it might
not be that the infection happened right
before then it might have been that
there was infectious exposure that
stayed below a particular level long
term and then known this is oftentimes
the case was like someone who has a long
term chronic herpes infection a physical
or emotional stressor can actually bring
about an outbreak that can happen with
lots of other kinds of infection
absolutely and the symptoms might not be
obviously connected to the type of
infection know they might know these
infections can spread to do
systems of the body so someone could
have infection in their jaw but they'll
they'll feel headaches or sometimes
those infections the bugs or the
biotoxins or inflammation can drop down
towards the gut or the respiratory
system then they're having symptoms in
those different areas so it's a lot of
hunting around to find out where the
infections are and what they are so for
those who are already deeply familiar
with these topics be patient as we can
to lay down the foundations we'll get
into deeper things but we want to kind
of start at the beginning so those who
aren't familiar get a lay of the land so
you mentioned biotoxins so what's the
difference between an infection and a
biotoxin the relationship so microbes
parasites
you know parasites smaller microbes they
they send out toxins as a way to protect
themselves from our our body's immune
system and and they're smart
so those toxins can actually win over
our immune system especially if we have
compromised in other ways so if we have
multiple infections if we have
environmental toxicity those bio toxins
which microbes and parasites send out
they can run their immune system down
even further yeah so mold is a pretty
classic example right serious you know
when people are dealing with mold in
their environment they might not
actually have any living mold in their
body they're just dealing with the micro
toxic byproducts that the mold produces
definitely and we can measure those
micro toxins so you started to
categorize types of infections you said
parasites and micro infections you want
to give a kind of lay of the land of the
categories of infection we look at in
some clinical cases yes so there can be
viruses epstein-barr virus died alone
cytomegalovirus coxsackievirus so these
are viruses that can be kind of
insidious we can exist person doesn't
know
um and then there's bacteria books there
can be gut bacteria that can be bacteria
in the respiratory system and and then
parasites parasites are a big one
they're difficult to test for so those
have to be more a clinical diagnosis
based on what the patient is telling me
based on their symptoms international
travel the other bugs they're easier to
test for now
parasites mean two things means
macroscopic parasites which means actual
bugs right multicellular things worms
and flukes and then microscopic protozoa
photos are usually easy to test for yeah
but I think of them as Suckerfish so if
you have those small protozoa our last
two sisters enterobacter I found find
those often and test I think of them as
soccer fish on sharks sharks are the
bigger the bigger parasites the ones you
mentioned look like those those can
exist I have patients sending me
pictures of what they find so this is a
fun topic because outside of like pin
worms and kids in the developed world
most people don't think about worms in
humans so they think about them in dogs
and cats and livestock right and they'll
they will deworm their dogs every year
they worm their cats if fleas are around
they know they have to deworm more and
they even know that we're not just
talking about GI worms we have heartworm
it's a common thing in dogs right so
we're like a worms can get into dog
hearts but they don't get into human
hearts right you know we're in other
organs so I think most people think
about worms in terms of tropical
infections in poor areas like guinea
worm but this is not a really good way
of thinking about it and yeah where you
started dr. Klink heart actually I think
does a lot of emphasis in macro scopic
parasite infections so talk to us more
about this these come these are very
common people more commonly people think
so I'm talking about complex chronic
illness right now um although I believe
that can also be well but
learning systems able to tolerate it dr.
clean heart uses the term uneasy
alliance he says we've got an uneasy
alliance with these parasites meaning
that our bodies are more likely have
such parasites if heavy metals and other
toxins make our body more of a breeding
ground for such parasites and so the
Alliance the uneasy alliances that these
parasites they they hold on to our toxic
burden for us but we have a better way
to deal with our toxic burden than to
have parasites that are sucking the
nutrients out of us or giving us GI
distress making last week so to just
kind of go into this a little bit we
obviously have a symbiotic relationship
with the bacteria in our microbiome and
with the healthy yeast in the microbiome
what we're saying here is that you can
have a symbiotic relationship in a
compromised condition but it's a
compromised symbiosis and so this is
species that wouldn't normally exist or
there would exist in much smaller
amounts in the case of parasites would
normally exist at all that actually
serve a symbian role yes but at a cost
exactly can you say a little bit about
the accumulation of toxins because I
don't think that is also a commonly
known topic you know one thing we've
noticed in medicine over the past
appears that illnesses are different
well suddenly we're seeing people with
more autoimmune conditions multiple
chemical sensitivity higher
susceptibility to infections so these
bugs have always been here Lyme is baby
air mold has been here the viruses were
here 15 years ago right why are we more
susceptible to them in a way that we
weren't before
why are suddenly people more susceptible
to chemicals these autoimmune conditions
why are we certainly creating suddenly
creating antibodies suddenly and
certainly creating antibodies to our own
self and I think it has a lot to do with
the onslaught of toxicity in our world
so in the air we breathe in the food we
eat and dr. Kling heart really talks
about this as well and so I do a ton of
detoxification work but I measure it
through labs on
heavy metals I'll measure s asides and
solvents and chemicals and we'll
definitely see these elevated without a
doubt in my patients with neurological
illnesses and no chronic infectious
diseases as well okay so I want to
actually get clear on the topic of a
subclinical condition whether about
subclinical infection or sub clinical
toxicology because again when we think
about heavy metal infections from a
traditional allopathic point of view
we're thinking about acute industrial
exposure and there's a you know level of
mercury exposure where we say oh there
was a cute mercury toxicity and we're
going to do some active kind of detox
chelation and we think about that as a
you know toxicology caused illness acute
very high level then we think about what
ideal levels are and the key is that
there's a pretty big range in between
ideal and actual toxic exposure which
we'd call a subclinical level of
toxicity it's not going to instantly
poison you might be asymptomatic but
it's gonna weaken the system you wanna
talk a little bit more about from that
perspective how often you see toxicity
deficiency and infectious things that
people wouldn't normally think of if
they were just thinking about normal
toxic levels yeah so my patients were
sick they've they've seen about 20
different doctors before they come to me
or before they come to Gordon medical
and they've been told you're fine your
labs look normal go home or this is all
in your head here's an antidepressant
top you with this hey my patients were
well poor or looking for a little bit
more optimization they're told oh it's
just age you just you're just now in
your 40s these things happen to you go
home your blood work but when you dig
deeper then you're able to find that
toxic load pretty high in my stick
population for sure borderline high in
people who are well to a level where I
want to decrease it for prevention so if
we take heavy metals for instance and as
one example of toxic load that according
to this model increases the
susceptibility for then infections
parasitic and other kinds of infections
because decreases immune function heavy
metals are maybe as controversial a
topic as you can get outside of maybe
vaccines right and medicine chelation is
a very controversial topic how to even
assess it
the problem with hair labs and urine
labs why provoked metal assessment is
tricky I'd be you can't be very happy if
listeners are interested to actually get
into the the body of clinical data here
and research on it but just from your
actual patient experience and clinical
experience not from not from literature
so when you when you do a provoked metal
challenge and you see elevated lead or
cadmium or mercury or whatever and then
you do some detox protocol using
chelation or binders or whatever you do
what do you see happen for people I see
quite a few things happened for sick
people I've seen nerve issues
go away nerve issues meaning things like
restless leg syndrome compulsions
we must disappear and sick people okay
I've seen cognition become more clear
for people they're less confused I've
seen I've seen
memory memory become better and the
immune system improved so they're
they're actually less susceptible to
other infections once I start to clear
the metals out and with regard to immune
system you mean not just that they're
getting sick less often but you can
actually
see biomarkers change immune biomarkers
absolutely yeah so now they say if you
have an uneasy alliance with parasites
would say you don't want to get rid of
the worms if you have them right away
without addressing metals if the worms
are actually accumulating metals and
protecting the body from it I would also
say that just getting rid of the metals
on its own might not work as well as if
you kind of work with the two together
so is that your approach absolutely so I
layer the approach so before I start to
kill off parasites it might be with
metals or other chemicals that I've seen
through laboratory tests mycotoxins as
well so I'll detoxify first to make the
body if you will less of a breeding
ground for the parents or microbes i
detoxify and then i I come in and I
start to bring the microbial count or
the parasite count down using either
herbs or pharmaceuticals and then I
rotate because I know that when I'm
killing microbes and parasites they dump
the metals and they also don't biotoxin
so I need to sweep out sweep that up
from the body if you will and discharge
it so because coming back to worms worms
flukes microscopic bugs even though they
might not be as acutely lethal to
someone as a particular bacteria or
virus might be it just freaks people out
to think about bugs inside of them
basically eating their tissue and so
it's a it's an interesting topic
now the reason they're hard to diagnose
is if you do a stool test you're
obviously only gonna see things that
show up in the GI tract not things would
be in other areas but they're not
necessarily shedding in the store right
unlike microbiome which is going to be
everywhere we might be looking at a
small number of these and particular
locations so you need many many stool
labs to have a high sense of accuracy
and not have false negatives and
obviously if we're talking about things
in other parts of the ball
you're not gonna see it in the stool you
have to depend on antibodies which are
fairly unreliable so diagnosis is tricky
so if you're largely working on clinical
presentation I am yeah so what do you
look for where you think maybe it's time
to treat parasites so um here are some
basic symptoms so a person person is
hungry all the time they're ravenous
they're not able to nourish themselves
they eat and they eat and I look at
their their micro nutrient labs low and
amino acids low in minerals vitamins
antioxidants but they're eating they're
eating a beautiful diet okay and above
other symptoms like gas and bloating
usually constipation could also show is
diarrhea
um aging of the anus as well is very
common so these would all indicate GI
parasites that would be actually taking
nutrients damaging the mucosal lining
making it hard to absorb nutrients
making GI issues how so if you're
looking at something like lungworm or
liver flukes or things that are you know
outside of the GI system what would you
look at you know that would be
symptomatic based on inflammation really
are they are they sensitive to
everything now I'm guessing I can't I
can't diagnose those that's your wild
guess and in treating for those directly
that's hard to do but if I treat the
system their whole body systemically I
believe but when their body when they're
when I can increase their immunity make
their body stronger those other very
much harder to diagnose parasite
infections can come down and the the
clean heart style parasite protocol has
a lot of systemic antiparasitics
[Music]
so when you when you run that protocol
on people again what do you find happens
as people go through the anti-parasitic
work yeah
they can get wiped out tired them all I
might have to slow them down on it I
might have to increase the consultation
methods as well so it's a dance and it's
different in the middle of it others
they feel nothing they're like I can't
even tell him taking medicine but I feel
increased energy some people are just
really really tired um and I think that
has to do with the body's ability to
detoxify so it's gonna be a different
response for each person and so then I
have to modulate based on on how that
person reacts so beyond what's happening
as they're in the protocol and their
body is obviously processing the meds
and processing died off if it's
happening what do you actually find as a
result of the protocol overall at the
end of the day they've got much more
increased health their their line
symptoms tend to go away I'm not
directly treating the line what I'm
doing is I'm treating the parasites and
treating the toxicity that makes the
body less susceptible to to the line
into other infections so there's an
overall sense of wellness after that
protocol is done for sure given that
we're not dealing with high reliability
diagnostic methods here but we're
dealing with wins clinical presentation
indicates and then what percentage of
people actually respond in cases where
people have some chronic illness they
doing with autoimmunity or nerdy Janek
rank fatigue how often do you see
parasites indicated and I'm talking
about people in your practice which
means they live in the Bay Area they
don't live in Saharan sub-saharan Africa
no it's very common very very common and
so remember how I said when I do a stool
test like we can see the smaller
pathogens right there they're easy to
see the amoebas the enterobacter blast
the sisters I see those every day on
regular people living in the in the Bay
Area optimizers on the healthy people I
see it on the sick people as well they
that's an indicator to me that there are
more parasites though I see it every day
in my practice on those stool tests so
the interesting thing here is that
people who are asymptomatic and healthy
as you mentioned earlier might be some
stressful incidents away from having an
infection that is actually being kept at
a relatively low level be able to go
into some kind of cascade definitely I'd
love to speak to that a bit so most of
my patients who are chronically ill they
may have businesses they run there some
of them are Olympians some of our
celebrities there are people who are
highly functional in the world and they
they had been for a long long time and
the key was all of a sudden something
happened and that is that is that is a
case of a subclinical infection suddenly
becoming big in somebody somebody who's
driven and having an having a very
engaged life suddenly they're not
something they're having to have
conversations about about we're needing
their house from mold you know
conversations that might make them look
a little bit weird in the world
all of a sudden yeah so this is
interesting right because somebody can
get in a car accident and have a sore
neck and do some massages or
chiropractic surest and then be fine or
they can get in the car accident and
then start having weird unexplained
symptoms and then have chronic fatigue
syndrome in a few months that lasts the
is debilitating or someone can have a
divorce and be emotionally bummed versus
emotionally bummed and then they get
chronic illness and so this is why
preventive medicine in healthy people is
so important is being able to increase
resilience to things that are going to
happen we're gonna have life events but
they don't have to result in the same
level of negative response actually
so this is this is do you have a lot of
patients who come just for the
preventative medicine and kind of
longevity wellness effects that's been
happening a lot over the past year year
and a half most definitely especially
here in the Bay Area people people are
really interested in optimization over
here come to me just for that and then
they're surprised at the things I might
find I'm surprised too
and the things I find subclinical
infections toxicity n-- the optimizer
they they want to test everything
they're interested they want to know
what do my hormones look like do I have
toxicity um
how about my neurotransmitters in my
adrenal function so they want to do all
the functional medicine tests because
they want the data on themselves so we
we mentioned that we wanted to talk
about the role of chronic infections and
this by OSIS and not just overall health
and chronic illness but specifically
mental emotional well-being so we can
start with any category then we can dive
in deeper but whether we're looking at
bacteria or mycoplasma or fungal or
parasitic what do you notice in terms of
the role that infections play when
people are dealing with anxiety sleep
issues depression etc yeah so the key is
that it's a sudden change in emotion so
it's normal or healthy people you know
to have some level of anxiety or
depression or different variabilities of
OCD okay that's very normal in the
healthy population but when suddenly we
go from having you know sweaty palms
before an important meeting to panic
attacks suicidal ideations severe mental
confusion right there that's the key for
me I know that there's a sub I don't I
don't want to say I know I am almost
certain there's a subclinical infection
that's that's turned that but so can you
describe the mechanism
right so how do we go from some kind of
infection to suicidal ideation and you
don't have to focus on suicidal ideation
but when we think of anxiety depression
ideation we think about neurologic
effects and our transmitter effects and
their hormone effects so can you tie the
the mechanisms together has been called
the second brain for a really good
reason so we have more neurons in our
gut than we do in our spinal cord and
90% of the communication of I'd say 90%
of the feedback of communication is from
our gut up to the brain not not
necessarily as much the reverse so the
gut really wants the brain as to what's
going on so it's a second brain in that
way it's not like we can make decisions
with our gut well that's a whole other
topic on in to me on intuition you know
but literally we can't we can't debate
politics or play music with art without
got the way that we can with our brain
but our gut having so many nerve not
neurons in it is like a second brain and
there can be neuro inflammation and that
inflammation can travel upwards to the
brain and that's what can cause changes
in mode can cause depression there's
also um an increase in cytokines as well
chemical mediators which increase
inflammation the more inflammation there
is in our gut that will travel upwards
through its exact like a highway a
neurological highway between the gut and
the brain so even though this has been a
popular idea in functional medicine
world for some time it just kind of
really entered the mainstream it's in
the last couple years thinking of
depression as being largely influenced
by a neuro inflammation and the idea of
depression almost being thought of as
rheumatism of the brain as you know
really kind of caught on and that I
don't think of it that way because I
don't think of depression is one thing I
think of it as lots of different things
with different ideologies but that's
certainly one of them right head trauma
can do it on its own and just purely
psycho-emotional things that are not
physiologic can but but whether we're
dealing with mold exposure or some kind
of subclinical infection in the body the
idea that it creates inflammation
inflammation that can cross blood-brain
barrier and cause more inflammation and
then the neuro inflammation affects
brain dynamics whether we're talking
about depression or anxiety or
neurologic issues or brain fog those can
all be mediated by neuro inflammation
yeah you know autism for instance I
think there are many many causes for
autism okay but well one thing the
research has shown is that children who
are autistic have a very different um
God milieu than unhealthy children oh I
think that's one that's one way to look
at one of the factors of autism although
of course it's if so many so when I
think about the gut brain
access I think about at least three
different dynamics one is the enteric
nervous system right the the neurologic
the neurons throughout the GI system
that then send a signal to the brain I
think about all the chemistry moving
from the gut into the blood which is
going to be both nutrients and possibly
toxins inflammation etc that can then
affect the environment that the nervous
system lives in and then I also think
about the microbiome and the microbiome
both in terms of the way that it
modulates genetic expression and the
fact that just from a really simple
point of view a huge percentage of our
primary neurotransmitters are produced
by the microbiome of the gut and so if
we've got 50 to 80 percent of our
dopamine serotonin gaba produced by
microbiome and we have some kind of
dysbiosis or infections driving
dysbiosis that's a pretty massive loss
of transmitter function immediately it
sure is
so do you do you assess for that do you
do things like look at neural hormones
neurotransmitters
and look at say gut microbiome an
infection kind of put those pieces
together to then assess priority of
treatments yeah I do so I'll look at
neurotransmitter function usually
people's neurotransmitters are quite low
that's common especially in complex
chronic illness and it's even common in
optimizers who've just worked so hard
they tank themselves a little bit so I
look at that and I look at their GI
system most of the time when I'm looking
at both I'm gonna find dysbiosis in the
gut mean that link I see very often so
these people will have a lot of yeast
different fungus is um again smaller
bacteria those will be seen and usually
I want to treat the gut first because
that's what's insulting um the the
production of neurotransmitters so I'm
treating the insult first then I work on
balancing the neurotransmitters I'll
layer them in I'll start working on the
gut maybe for a month and then layer in
neurotransmitter treatment on top of it
concurrently but give a got a head start
so this is a pretty common best practice
and naturopathic medicine starting the
gut we've obviously got the mucosal
system which is everywhere that the
environment connects to our body that
isn't skin eye sinuses mouth your
genital bronchioles got you've got then
into an infection there you have
infection in the blood you can have
infections in the cells why do you start
with the gut that is the production of
the immune system
and and that's where all begins ever
oftentimes of people have mycotoxins or
fungus and their sinuses I may start
with their sinuses first because it's
such a bony concentrated area I just I
just want to give them some relief and I
also know that infections from here they
travel downwards quickly so I want to
clear this up first and then I'll go the
gut depending on on the severity of the
science infection I see a lot of people
quite severity in their sinuses and
proximal to the brain is relevant mm-hmm
same with dental infection that's right
corner wouldn't be extent infections for
sure say that again
people turn up people turn a corner in
complex chronic illness big circle
dental infections so let's talk about
that I think as far as biologic
dentistry goes most people are aware
that mercury fillings are a great thing
and that may be the proper removal of
mercury is a good idea I think that's
the most common idea the idea of
subclinical infection other than
systemic gingivitis is a less well-known
idea do you want to talk about that
definitely but I also want to talk about
the mercury first you'll be surprised
how many people come to me saying that
they had their metal amalgams removed by
a non-biological dentist have swallowed
the mercury is vaporized up and they are
sick yeah and and I will measure their
blood murky it's high I'll do we are in
provoked test that's high and once we
start to get the mercury out there's a
big difference in their cognition and
some of them have come with neurological
symptoms as well those as well shift so
the the best practice there is if you're
gonna remove mercury go to someone who
actually knows what they're doing
exactly systemic dentist so I pretty
much always recommend people who are
trained in Huggins protocol is that also
you do yeah all right so speaking of
Huggins protocol let's continue on the
topic of sub acute dental infections so
root canals have been improperly
improperly extracted I'm sorry I'm gonna
backtrack when wisdom teeth have been
improperly extracted and underneath root
canals there can be some clinical
infections so in addition a small idea
they're asymptomatic they can't feel it
but they have a lot of brain fog I'd
have headaches diminish
trigeminal neuralgia they have no idea
there's an infection in their jaw so I
asked them have you had your wisdom
teeth extracted do you have root canals
okay so when people have infections up
in here those are my two questions right
away I send them to a biologic slash
systemic dentist because those dentists
have what's called a CT scan and a cat
an ikat annsofi t scan which allows us
to see small slices of the bone and find
localized infections which aren't seen
on regular panorex digital x-rays but
not seen with the naked eye they're
they're missed in traditional dentistry
just downright missed okay and so once
those infections are cleaned up that's
when I see a lot of head symptoms
resolved do you run the Huggins PCR
assessments for infection also to look
at the species and load our biological
dentist does yeah yeah you'd be
surprised by what comes back yeah
interesting infections yeah so so will
you explain for people what is an
improper extraction and why would that
lead to infection and why would root
canal leak infection you know they're
small they're small areas an improper
extraction could be leaving an area not
sutured well not closed well it stays
open
I've had people I had had a material
like gauze left in there um then they've
had had to have the gauze removed and
then it doesn't heal that doesn't heal
properly so there's there's many
different ways when the surgery isn't
isn't quite quite perfect and that's a
finicky some area and like I said before
a lot of bone in there small compact
areas so that's when infections can
happen I think with regard to extraction
what wisdom teeth or other extractions
one of the common things is even if the
surgery is done well there is a ligament
that connects the
to the bone and that if Seligman is not
fully removed then it's dead tissue and
then how did the body or a tissue
typically that's a microbes job and so
then you have a pocket that with some
dead tissue in it where you end up
having breeding ground for microbe also
if there was infection in the tooth to
begin with it might have gone into the
bone if it wasn't cleaned all the way so
the Huggins protocol is process for they
make sure to go it get rid of the
ligament go into the bone stimulate bone
bleeding so it actually heals more
deeply and you get you get removal of
the infection and no dead tissue left
right which is the same thing with root
canal in terms of dead tissue right you
end up getting a tooth left it has no
immune system in it but is permeable so
that all those miles of dentin tubules
can be a place that infection can hide
out yeah and then those infections
travel they can travel upwards towards
the brain they can travel down so
infections travel biotoxins trouble
inflammation from those sites the same
goes with fineness NEC issues so let's
talk about the sinus thing right so with
the dental infections someone kind of a
dental infection where they don't they
go to their normal dentists and their
Dennis's everything's fine right
they don't have dental issues they don't
have gingivitis because if we're looking
at something that's maybe at the very
root of a root canal tooth you're not
gonna see that unless you do one of
those diagnostics that we discussed but
it might be affecting ongoing immune and
inflammatory dynamics to the blood so
the the thing that might get better
right the thing that might have gotten
worse is over the course of ten or
twenty years some very slow just effect
on decreased homeo dynamics of the whole
system and what might get better is some
systemic thing that's not localized at
all right so the key thing there is that
we're not looking at mouth issues as a
symptom to assess we're looking at any
kind of systemic issues right so sinus a
similar ring series so you're not
talking about people who have chronic
sinus infections only know
definitely not so then what would
indicate for you and then how would you
go about testing in sections and the
sinuses yeah so it's often people who've
had mold exposure they know they've been
in a water damaged place a lot of people
come to me for a mold exposure because
all of a sudden they are sick when they
were fine and I know I want to test
their sinuses right away you know
because they've been breathing that so
um a test from Mark Long's which is a
kind of staph infection that's
antibiotic resistant Louis resistant to
many different antibiotics that's common
and people will find toxin illness mold
illness and mine so I'll test from our
cons test for other funguses and
bacteria very typically I find those
things this is a swab swab measles
yellow so if someone can come see a
functional medicine doctor get a swab
check it out treat it awesome if if they
can't
what does I'm switching to treatment I'm
bouncing around a little bit but what if
something someone can do for sinus
hygiene on their own that can help to
decrease infectious load in the sinuses
it can do neti pot rinses oh just some
filtered water put a little bit of a
little bit of salt in there hey then he
popped both sides that really helps
clear things out they can use I really
am a fan of argent and silver so that
can also help clear out infections
there's they can nebulize it there's
nasal sprays for it as well or put it in
the neti pot exactly how about the
xylitol nasal sprays yep back to so I
think that you know unless someone has
an Ayurvedic background most people
don't think of nasal cleaning as part of
their daily or regular hygiene like they
think of teeth cleaning but you would
suggest that people do I do
I suggest think do it on a regular basis
at least three times a week you know
it's a
a place where we can harbor bugs for
sure we have more cysts more of a
susceptibility to bugs now than we ever
did before due to environmental toxins
and yeah and travel where the bugs from
any part of the world are now everywhere
and antibiotic resistance and pesticide
use and etc yeah and also I think
there's there's an obsession with over
sanitizing and people using too much
Purell it it too much hand sanitizer not
letting children play in the dirt we're
not allowing our immune systems to be
exposed to the beneficial bacteria which
allow our immune system to become
stronger so actually on that topic when
you think about using germicidal soaps
the triclosan which is the most common
actual antibiotic put in the soaps how
often do you see that show up when
you're doing environmental toxicity to
cancer and the link to antibiotic
resistance of any infections that happen
to be there yeah mm-hmm yeah I've seen a
lot of triclosan show up on on
toxicology profiles also yeah and
typically find that addressing
infections and those people takes more
work it does I also see a lot of
parabens show up so those are beauty
products and our show and our and our
soaps and shampoos and and makeup so you
know there's a whole new trend towards
holistic beauty as well and so similarly
if someone was gonna want to have a hand
soap that had some antibacterial
properties essential oils yeah lavender
tea tree thyme oregano yeah okay so we
talked about hygiene for the nose how
about when we're talking about
subclinical infections in the mouth
hygiene for the mouth this sides going
to see a biologic dentist and get those
primary things done are there any things
beyond just basic teeth brushing you
recommend yeah for sure flossing that's
basic but it's so important because that
that's right in the tissues but um oil
pulling can really help tunnel scraping
now we're talking about more Ayurvedic
methods but maybe shirt later work so
describe those two because oil pulling
oil pulling in tongue scraping are both
Ayurvedic but they might not be familiar
to everybody yeah so sometimes freaking
a little tool which I'm actually you
take that tool and you brush it against
your tongue and it removes biofilm and
coatings from those little bugs and then
then gargling with salt after that you
know and then oil pulling is is taking
um oil which has antimicrobial effects
and and um holding it in the mouth and
and swishing it around and that also
pulls pulls microbes the way that I
generally recommend having people do the
oil pulling is whether it's coconut oil
or sesame oil or they get a specialized
oil pulling premade product that has
essential oils in it is that they're
actually vigorously swishing until the
oil and saliva have mixed and it
actually looks like saliva it looks
white rather than yellow when they spit
usually ten or fifteen minutes and the
the hypothesis there is that you have
some antimicrobial properties in the oil
that it helps the integrity of the
tissues the gums right it's emollient
but also that as as an oil as a fat that
it creates an osmotic pressure for fat
soluble toxins to come into the oil and
then get spit out so it is a way to
detox um fat soluble toxins which
supposedly has been microscopy verified
I can't verify that myself but yeah what
about water picking I can definitely
help clean between the gums for sure
that can be food stuck in there unless
of course we'll track microbes but just
washing that out yeah I do uh I add
silver to the water pick and use that
and
decreases the chance of deep pockets
definitely the silver will kill off
microbes as well alright good so then
what about to where we're discussing now
some kind of home methods people can do
outside of the medical therapies so what
about with the gut we were talking about
you know if someone actually has
microscopic parasites in the gut they're
gonna have to go get appropriate
diagnosis treat that it'll probably
involve meds if they've got dysbiosis
protozoa those are gonna be very
customized protocols if someone doesn't
have the resources to go work with a
functional medicine doctor right away
what are some basic things that are
generally well indicated for gut
microbiome health yeah so eating
probiotics so these are foods that are
high in the beneficial bacteria things
like kefir sauerkraut miso kimchi
kombucha hay eating prebiotics these are
the foods that that feed the healthy
bacteria these are mostly vegetables and
fruits but common ones are apples pears
celery artichoke lentils bounty bugs
love those healthy fats as well those
are gonna help to decrease inflammation
in the gut
avocado coconut olive oil chia seeds
hemp seeds and things that we want to
avoid we want to avoid the overuse of
antibiotics like they for sure there's a
there's a place for antibiotics I will
prescribe them to people
no and unnecessary but there's they're
often over prescribed and then
prescribed when they're not needed so to
avoid the overuse of antibiotics
definitely to avoid processed sugar
processed foods those feed the bad
bacteria artificial sweeteners
artificial foods and preservatives feed
the pathogenic bugs mm-hmm and what do
you think about for GI system in
particular what do you think about
fasting and fasting colonics
salt water flushes other things for kind
of taking the load off the GI system
yeah I think it's important to have an
or
and a rectal route when we're trying to
clean the system so colonics definitely
especially when returning get rid of
parasites animals for sure what else did
you ask about fasting fasting yeah
fasting it depends depends on what
people can tolerate but if people can
tolerate even a bone broth fast just for
three days that can really help to fix
leaky gut syndrome it can help to
restore the permeability of the gut
membrane a water fast can help to reset
the metabolism some people can tolerate
it so you know it depends on on
tolerance but those who can tolerate it
can help reset the system so talk to me
about infections in other parts of the
body so we've mostly talked about within
the GI system so far including the mouth
and then the the nasal and sinuses were
just still part of the mucosal system
talk to me about like infections in the
prostate and urogenital kinds of
infections yeah they're common I see
them I see them commonly actually in
people who have autoimmune conditions
and complex chronic illness you know
that the basic UTI shows up in the
general population as well but I do see
these infections recurrent for people
who are sick so we work with that with
those herbal II just at one I want to
start with the gut because the
inflammation I believe starts and
they've got and it can work its way down
to go to the lower areas what have you
noticed about the relationship I know
you worked at an integrative oncology
center have you noticed about the
relationship of say you know people have
prostate cancer elevated PSA leading in
the prostate cancer and increased
infectious load prostate infection
have you noticed those I mean obviously
we know cervical cancer in HPV right
there's a lot of clinical research on
the HPV EBV mycoplasma and prostate
cancer
you speak to that yeah we can definitely
definitely test it for those you know
for the toxic load and people of them
shouldn't say toxic load the microbial
load again through a stool test
definitely I've seen correlations there
and I think that um I think it is is
it's the toxins and again sorry the
biotoxins that those microbes spit out
that that caused inflammation in the
body travel downwards and then such
close proximity to the gut so when
you're thinking about cognitive health
mental emotional health obviously
infection is one component right
obviously nutrition is a component and
hormones are a component there's a
number of physiologic components
biotoxins are a component and then
obviously you have to address psychology
and their actual life right
relationships how often when you're
dealing with mental emotional dynamics
for people that have a physiologic
origin
do you see infection or at least
dysbiosis involved all the time but the
thing is that people who come to me are
half more than half them are complex
chronically ill patients right away I
searched for infections and I find them
and you know research has shown that
people with complex chronic illness are
more prone to depression and anxiety so
I see those hand-in-hand every day many
times every day so are there any other
recommendations you want to share you
mentioned avoid antibiotics that are
unnecessary and avoid processed sugar
and some dietary guidelines besides just
saying gut if we wanted to say how to
decrease infectious burden and increase
immune function systemically what are
other home recommendations that are
generally a good idea for people yeah so
you know definitely um my patients
travel a lot and to be careful when when
traveling and even when camping
not to drink in water when you're in
developing countries to make sure your
fruits and vegetables are cooked and at
home to make sure your fruits and
vegetables are washed thoroughly that um
in in cilantro and you know the small
leafy vegetables there are some really
tiny bugs that can get stuck in there we
can eat them and they can they can cause
trouble for us as well and you obviously
don't just mean bugs you mean eggs
they're invisible
hey do you know what is washed
thoroughly mean just like a couple drops
of hydrogen peroxide or vinegar in in in
in the sink that you filled with water
leave leave your vegetables or fruit in
there but particularly the ones with the
small leafy's well like ten minutes and
then wash that off thoroughly with water
that helps that's a pretty extreme
measure but these are for people who you
have a propensity to illness for sure
and that might be many things but one
part of propensity to actually get
infection from what someone needs and
their fruits and vegetables would have
to do with their stomach acid levels
right so mmm
any any thoughts or guidelines on
increasing hydrochloric acid production
and as a first part of stomach community
of GI immunity yeah you know you can
actually take um you can take a little
bit of hydrochloric acid if you have if
you tend to have um reflux it's usually
because you don't have enough acid which
is listings countered to it intuitive
but not enough acid in in in the stomach
causes the sphincter to actually open
and release acid upwards so if that's
happening then for sure that that that's
often a diagnostic of not having enough
acid I'll just give people some a little
bit of hydrochloric acid supplement to
take um having a more alkaline diet can
help as well so say what the rough
overview of that is yeah so um definite
high-end veggies high in fruit not not
fruit that some have a high glycemic
load not super sugary fruits of course
you can enjoy those as well but you know
to have those limited a lot of veggies
low and grains mostly paleo style
unsustainable meats if you have any
books on diet nutrition that you think
are good starter books for people you
like to recommend yeah um Kim Schneider
I like her book doctor Perlmutter's
books are interesting things doctor
Gondry's books those are interesting as
well plant paradox yes yeah okay and
then so obviously if people are wanting
to really address the topic of their
microbiome and infection this is
something that's very well served
working with a functional medicine
integrative medicine doctor that can do
the appropriate assessment and treatment
protocols what do you recommend someone
look for if they're wanting to find a
doc to work with yeah there's a couple
things I think doctors are very highly
trained in in frontal medicine that's
where functional medicine began really
for and MDS who've had a functional
medicine training also quite wonderful
as well so definitely to have some do
you want as a medical license whether
it's an MD or an MD and someone who's
got some functional medicine training
now for the training around parasites
that's a whole different ballgame
that's not taught that's not taught in
regular nash traffic school regular
medical school or in functional medicine
in general infectious diseases that's
that's you've got to find someone who's
particularly trained in that so someone
who's trained with doctor clean heart
for example or who's trained with dr.
Gordon here according medical or dr.
Anderson here so there's certain clinics
who specialize in these things and
that's rare to find in our education
system and did you say when we're
talking earlier that for people who
listen this podcast who happened to be
in or could come to the Bay Area and
want to come to Gordon medical and work
with you work with the doc said that you
had something to offer yeah absolutely
for so patients how many patients who
are here let's think of this podcast if
they're new to me you know for 150
dollars off an initial visit with me and
for existing patients 150 dollars off of
any new procedure with me awesome is
there any like a code that someone would
need to use yeah let's use a code neuro
hacker okay that's fun alright so this
is I think this is a good introduction
to the topic of subacute you know
subclinical chronic infections and that
this has a role in you know possibly has
a role in cancer autoimmunity nerd ijen
chronic illness fatigue energy but also
in mental emotional health and and if
people want to you know come work with
you awesome if they want to you know
find someone you give them some
resources to find but it anyone working
on chronic illness knows that there's a
lot of personal responsibility they have
to take to figure this out because
typically they're working with a number
of different doctors and therapists to
kind of figure out what they actually
need is there anything else that you'd
like to share with people today just
kind of closing thoughts on these topics
yeah yeah these complex chronic
illnesses can happen to anybody and
that's what I see and it's what it's
what surprises me every time actually
I've seen hundreds and hundreds of
hundreds of these cases every time it's
a bit of a surprise how healthy the
person was before how functional they
were how driven and engaged they were in
their lives suddenly something happens
in life it's just not the same anymore
so prevention is really really important
so getting diagnostics and understand
what is underneath all of this I want to
talk a little bit about medical
actually and we didn't talk about
Diagnostics but medical omics is um it's
actually research that Gordon medical is
doing with dr. Bob not na vo and UC San
Diego and it is a test we're looking at
biochemical markers in real time so it
can predict your health and it can
predict illness in a way that nothing
else can so it's looking at organic
acids amino acids vitamins minerals
different lipids in a way that no other
tests can right now research is still
being done but it's predicted so you
know we learned from the human genome
product project that you know genes are
only predictive of 10% of our illnesses
metabolomics is looking at these
chemicals in real time and it's actually
looking at the cross between your genes
and toxicity or your genes and whatever
is is approaching you to create either
either wellness or illness so it that is
I think it's going to change the face of
medicine so I mean I'm excited to be
involved in that yeah and to the work
you're doing it at Gordon medical is one
of the few facilities that I know of
that's actually doing cutting-edge
research grade metabolomics along with
actual clinical Diagnostics to start
looking for correlation to be able to
then train the software system on the
interpretation of the metabolomic yeah
yeah so we just you know published some
research research on chronic fatigue
syndrome being able to distinguish that
from healthy people as well as
depression on on it for autoimmunity and
toxicity that was very very exciting so
metabolomics might not be a familiar
term for everybody here do you want to
just say a little bit about what the
metabolism why that would be an
interesting diagnostic method yeah yeah
so metabolomics is the measure of
molecules in the body that
way less than a thousand killer Dalton's
so enzymes way tens of thousands of
killer Dalton so in metabolomics we're
measuring amino acids organic acids like
I said before minerals vitamins all
these fats as well so all these um all
these phytochemicals that make up the
cells that make up the organelles
organelles are the little organs that
make up the cell as well so now we're
looking at what our cellular responses I
was looking at the true biochemistry
biochemical makeup the body what's
interesting with metabolomics is it's in
its in real time so the expression of
your environment meaning your genes and
so it gives us true true validation on
moving forward right what when we can
start to predict the results that's only
gonna have the validation that we're
looking for why it's exciting me a lot
yeah and so that people understand the
word I'll just say a little bit more so
with metabolomics we're looking at the
metabolic byproducts of cells and so
cells are taking in energy sources from
carbohydrates from fat from wherever
they're taking the energy and then
they're processing that energy and doing
all the interesting things cells do and
then they're producing metabolic waste
products byproducts and so that's a you
know it's twenty six hundred or so
metabolites that we know of a few
hundred primary ones and basically
everything that's happening in the cell
ends up showing up in the metabolic
byproducts that are coming out of the
cell that we can look at in the blood
looking at what's happening inside the
cell is kind of tricky but what's being
released from the cell gives us some
pretty good forensics of what's
happening in the cell and so whether the
cell is affected by infection or
toxicity or deficiency and what's
actually happening at the level of
genetic transcription not just the
genome but the epigenome should all show
up in the metabolomics now being able to
interpret all that is the work over the
next few years right that's a very
exciting field yeah exciting yeah I'm
happy all their prototyping that and so
anyone who comes
- Gordon medical for their own work has
the chance to actually be part of that
research definitely cool thank you
nafisa thank you so much for being here
with us this was interesting if people
want to actually find you and be able to
come where what's the website it's
Gordon medical calm okay all the contact
information is there yeah great I'll
come from all over the world all over
the country they come and stay for a
month they're longer get their treatment
go back home come back again and then we
also have Bay Area people who come of
course as well yeah yeah alright so we
will put that link in the show notes for
those who are interested and it was a
delight to have you thank you thank you
thank you for listening to collective
insights for the full show notes on this
episode and for more great interviews
visit us at neuro hacker.com slash
collective insights if you liked this
episode please subscribe to the podcasts
and leave us a 5-star review on iTunes